welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
introductions here hello everyone and
welcome to the stoah stoah is a digital
campfire where we go here in dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of this moment I am Raven a host
here at the stoah so basically what
we're gonna do is no harness is gonna
have the floor for about 20 minutes here
and then we will open up to questions
from the audience
yo.hannes is a philosopher in the wild
bringing the ancient tradition of
philosophy keeping the ancient Rishon of
philosophy alive asking real questions
about what is the meaning of life what
is the meaning of death and being he is
the founder of the hulky on
thinkers guild and currently teaching a
course called idleness with dignity
today he will be discussing leisure as
the basis for the coming Renaissance and
with that I bring you
Johannes
thank you very much Raven thank you very
much Peter for inviting me
yeah the talk is on leisure on Scola in
the Greek sense I'll do something a
little bit old-fashioned I'll read and
give a proper lecture which rhythm which
means to read and then we'll we'll take
questions so the question of leisure is
not a question of what we do when we
have some free time from work rather it
is the question of all questions the
question of Scola and truly sure Moosa
asked the Chairman monocular says is the
question that founds civilization it is
the basis of civilization Athens was
born Plato tells us in his dialogue
critius on the basis of scholar when a
scholar arrived in the midst of
Athenians for them their thoughts had
turned towards the Plenty the abundance
of beings and of course also to an
appreciation of the old and their
ancestors this our age is good to be
moans and his Maxim's and reflections is
unholy since nothing is allowed to come
into its own which means nothing is
allowed to ripen
a great forgetting said in centuries ago
and the reckoning now has come we have
forgotten who we are who we yet do not
remember who we have always been goethe
here continues the activity of commerce
the rush and rustle of paper money
the swelling up of debts to pay debts
all these are the monstrous elements to
which in these days a young man is
exposed
what is debt other than the utter abyss
which sucks as empty and leaves our
world voided of meaning usury is an
existential trap a tempest idle
destruction of all genuine access to
time and history
the freezing of a memory of who we are
and have always been what good it begins
to see here already is what Heidegger
will come to call the insatiable will to
will that will sever more and can only
give itself a ground if it continues to
will more and ever greater costs for all
and ever more forests and greater effort
and ever-smaller dividends and yields a
tiredness has ruled us for long already
if we are honest to ourselves a sluggish
tiredness that masquerades as positive
thinking immediately prescribed optimism
keeping calm and carrying on hiding a
frail nurse and portraying ourselves a
strong-willed and forceful and
competitive but caving immediately when
the subtle I'm Ken eNOS of existence
begins to spit heavy empty go-lucky
happy-go-lucky attitude that we are
forced to display we live not in a polis
there is a mirror of the good order of
the cosmos we do not live in a virtuous
Poly's of fellow humans who cooperate
but an uncanny will work as Nietzsche
calls it we exist in the grind of the
quote from Nietzsche total economic
management of the earth but earth has
begun to fight back how sick and corrupt
and and he human is a system that
collapses if the world stands still for
only two weeks who and what are these
concealed God's many prey to and sacrif
for unbeknownst to them is this a world
fit for humans where stillness is a sin
what we have forgotten is what the
Greeks called Scola leisure or Musa in
German which is not free time from work
but which we are that we are sometimes
granted and granted if and only if all
basic needs are met no is anyone who can
see what drives this planetary I'm Kenny
will work the will to will that wills
itself and wilt itself sir why because
just because it is so anyone who sees
this knows that never will all needs be
met for the will itself is lack
fundamental lack leisure does that come
once all basic needs and wants and
desires are met instead leisure itself
is the cradle of civilization of the
well-ordered Paulus the planet has
ground to a halt
Atlantis is sinking again Plato tells us
in his dialogue creatures Atlantis this
most magnificent city of its time began
to lose its ways when the Atlanteans
directed their sense towards lack but
command the continuous inflow of goods
to their to steal the insatiable
appetites became dominant their harbor
the harbor of Atlantis never stood still
they turned their days into a restless
frenzy and their nights in today's I'm
Kenny will work indeed in the same
dialogue Plato tells us how Athens
became Athens the palace of the goddess
Athena the garden of the fruit of the
fruits of which we still enjoy Athenians
before they became who they were
directed their sense toward lack they
had no room for a knowledge of the old
of that which has always been they found
no stance to take in the midst of beings
and scholar was nowhere to be found
which is very briefly slowly the word in
Greek comes from a hane which means to
have to hold so Scala literally is that
which grants hold a stance in the mid
of beings but once the Athenians
directed their sentence towards scholar
they were to remember - what's the
stance in the midst of beings they began
to remember the future they were able to
remember who they had always been Scola
the spirit of true leisure entered them
arrived in their midst and they found
the hold to ground the palace that
became Athens the true garden with their
sense directed at Scola their spirit
filled with it Athenians turned to what
Plato calls me - lugia mythology the
knowledge of the old of the ancestors
the oldest Aristotle tells us is the
name for being taught T and a night that
which has always been being the question
of being which we are forgetting is a
reminder of who we have always been but
the will - will blinds our eyes and
hearts for this deep memory and true
inner ring memory memorizing coming to a
census bringing into the inner of our
hearts of who we are the will - will
wills us to be enslaved by debt numb
from experience and death machines the
will - will wills us to kill time rather
than allowing for the wonders of boredom
to disclose to us the wonders of the
world and who we are for it is in our
epoch through the hora wakui also and
the aura of emptiness that meaning can
begin to shine forth directing our sense
our senses again - scholar the spirit of
true leisure will take hold of us and
remind us of our ancestors or the old of
being it is then that we can begin again
to build proper cities houses fit for
humans an economy an economy the normals
of the house that's what this means the
law of the house that does not destroy
the earth does not deplete meaning and
does not use usury it is then that we
could begin again to dwell and as
Heidegger points out genuine dwelling
means to protect the earth but does not
mean to destroy the earth in search for
the insatiable lust for comfort
would she use the earth as a gas station
but we must begin again to think first
and of course now currently an obscene
haste rules more than perhaps before the
corona pandemic and this obscene haste I
see in wanting to act wanting to find a
cure wanting to establish a new order of
the world and as we saw with an essay
that went around this week which was
it's time to build in all capital
letters
but what BR yes I argued for was to have
more stuff if only we had had in
hindsight more stuff we would have been
saved but thinking is what we have to do
first contemplate perhaps also we must
think we if we still are these so on
log on or on the living being that fine
finds itself and holds itself in logos
we must gather ourselves to come to our
senses to the genuine human sense which
is a sense of Goethe still speaks off
and sue remembers and greater remembers
also that all that is intelligent has
already been thought what we are to do
is think again through the echoes of
truth and suddenly we are thrown back to
ourselves looking for a stance for
something to hold on to we will not find
it in an obscene haste we might find a
stance again if we begin to be idle with
dignity which is to say that we find our
being human what it means to be human
only in this being suspended and the
proper need to ground ourselves would
like to read a passage from Nietzsche's
gay science which is entitled mostly on
to music on leisure and idleness the gay
science is the book which is already
pregnant with Sara through straw the
profit of the eternal recurrence and
also of the recurrence of the tragic
sense
this is Nietzsche the breathless haste
of America with which they work is
already beginning to infect old Europe
with its ferocity and is spreading a
lack of spirituality
Geist loses tied like a blanket even now
one is ashamed of resting and prolonged
reflection almost gives people a bad
conscience one things with a watch in
one's hand even as one eats one's lunch
while reading the latest news of the
stock market one lifts as if one always
might miss out on something rather do
anything than nothing
this principle too is merely a string to
throttle all culture and good taste just
as all forms are visibly perishing by
the haste of the workers the feeling
perform itself the ear and eye for the
melody of movements are also perishing
the proof of this may be found in the
universal demand for gross obviousness
in all those situations in which human
beings wish to be honest with one
another for once in their associations
with friends women relatives children
teachers pupils leaders and princes one
no longer has time or energy for
ceremonies for being obliging in an
indirect way for a splean conversation
and for any odium at all end of quote
so without leisure without idleness
we are spiritless we are numb there is
no poetry in such world all enjoyment is
already only relaxation as if we were an
ox under a yoke a castrated animal
carrying a burden it does not see the
question of latter and idleness
make no mistake is not some question
about what we do in our spare time or
now that we are locked in this is not to
say true leisure just means to read some
Aristotle either all that we have some
now we have some time to ourselves know
the question of scholar properly and
directly concerns itself with the
question what it means to be human too
into the spirit of true scollay or true
leisure means to begin to remember a
future we have never known in 1949 the
German Catholic philosopher Josef PIPA
Popish tan essay entitled Musa unquote
which is usually translated as letter at
the basis of culture there's something
lost in this translation Musa is
scolding the true spirit of foundational
leisure but Colt does not mean culture
it means worship without the divine we
are only ever idolizing ourselves and a
fake pleasure true ceremony is only
possible with a few to the divine and
with sacrifice and only then would
sacrifice can we also safeguard the
earth in his essay PIPA reminds his
readers of the grand tradition of the
Occident the land of dusk of its
contemplative caste which once was of
those who by meditating and
contemplating looked after that which is
people fears that we all would become
workers in a world of total work he
reminds his readers that those who
prayed to God before bedtime sleep
better but he also says that it would be
absurd to assume that someone just prays
in order to sleep better in order to
increase efficiency or effective attea
of sleep as if praying were but self
idolatry of the human being
little did he know that meditation think
in all its various disguises a few
decades after his death in the late 90s
would offer just this mad thing that we
now meditate in order to sleep better
but what does it mean to meditate one of
the oldest sentences of Occidental
wisdom comes from periander which is in
Greek Meli Melita thumpin take into care
and consideration everything there is
beings in the whole to meditate means to
care for beings deeply and profound
meditating in order to perform better
whatever task or to get over anxiety for
example is avoiding and desertification
of the meaning of meditation and hence
one of the pale horses from which
nihilism has pillaged our lands and
pastures let us begin rather to direct
our sensor mentions inner sense of being
human towards the spirit of true latter
the plenty in fullness at the heart of
things the exuberance of being the gift
that is thinking itself for then we
begin to remember what we have always
already been and we build towards a
genuine future and not some fantasy our
economic systems whatever isn't they are
are all predicated on fundamental lack
yes humans I agree have needs very
obviously this is undeniably true
however the needs with which we are
concerned in our economic systems and
our political systems too however only
the most immediate their only material
needs we only ever consider the useful
it is not meaning sense our most
fundamental need but for the economic
and political systems that we know today
meaning has no place how can we redirect
on our human sense perhaps by taking
again the meditative stance of leisure
and by moving beyond utilitarian
calculations consider heidegger's
interpretation of Chuang sees the
useless tree the tree no longer bears
any fruit and hence the person who owns
the tree wants to cut it down but Chuang
T invites the peasant to begin to see
something else
another possibility another dimension
even for the tree the tree is useless
yes nothing can be made of it still the
tree precisely for its uselessness
invites us to sit underneath it simply
in order to sit and so to come to our
senses again
this is similar for the meaning of
things one cannot do anything with
meaning meaning is profoundly useless
for the uncanny calculations of the
wheel work in fact one could even go as
far as saying that the uncanny machinery
requires meaninglessness for its
operations the useless is that which is
beyond utilitarian calculations and
hence withdraws from them yet
thanks to this withdrawal other
dimensions of meaning occur and open up
in which the instrumental in the
utilitarian have no place true leisure
itself is useless for the operations of
the will to will but as such true
leisure is the source of meaning for
that which is useless is untouchable and
enduring thank you very much
thank you your highness so now we're
going to move into the question and
answer period so if you would like to
put your question in the chat and I will
then call your name and you can unmute
yourself and ask your question directly
to johannes and i'm just gonna start by
asking a few questions for you Oh
so as I'm listening to what you're
saying and I've been also taking in some
of your other lectures it seems like
II
integration or the idea of idleness
coming at it from our cultural
perspective now is actually a massive
challenge because I can imagine moving
from this idea of like Oh instead of
working I'll I'll be idle but it'll be
because I want to be more productive or
because I want to sleep better and I was
thinking about how sleep actually might
be a way for the you know the Western
human to kind of get into this idea of
idleness what would you have to say
about about sleep and and idleness its
yeah the way we think of sleep is that
we need our eight hours of sleep in
order to be productive the next day and
I just saw today actually this is an
advice for anyone who's here to sign up
to Tom Hodgkins and newsletter he's he's
just a fascinating eccentric Brit
anyways he's just I'm to listen to but
but Tom said today Bob bosses are
getting worried because it actually is
now it's now possible to to work from
home etc but sleep is is crucial and
actually there is in in the Occident or
in Western in the Western cradle there
are examples of off the appreciation of
sleep for completely different reason
than we now think of it nets and
Heraclitus and chose if people mentions
this actually in his essay on you know
leisure as the basis of culture the our
clients assess that those who sleep
participate in the world that they're
not cut off from the world they
participate in it not in the sense of
how we would probably see it you know
you sleep you're eight nine hours and
then you're productive again in the next
day know it's this and it's so foreign
to us to say this when someone who
sleeps just by sleeping the official
English translation is participates in
the business of the world participates
then in what what happens and this is
some someone like Andrew tagging for
example who mostly at this point
meditates and says when he meditates the
philosophical questions
just come to him from meditating this is
it's it's I'm honored it's it's unusual
now for us to think of for example the
priest caste which you know what what
they do is they think or they meditate
or they pray and in so doing they Co
they they they Cohen enlighten the world
but and it's a completely non productive
it's completely non utilitarian it can't
be measured it can't be called it it can
be qualified it cannot be evaluated and
and yes so the way one can begin to
think about sleep is not that it makes
you in any sense it's there to make you
more productive for anything but it is
that in sleep something fun foundational
happens which is that it brings you in
tune with being speaking this high
daguerreian way or with the world in a
way that that being awake doesn't so we
have to take it seriously and on that
level to but that there's something that
dreams tell us about us and about the
world
yeah and so another thing I was I was
wondering about is there's this idea
that we will get to idleness through
automation through through these like
structures I mean this is there's this
idea going around of like fully
automated luxury capitalism as you know
the patch of the future that's going to
release us from this idea of of work and
this will to will
how do you see that fitting into this
idea of idleness do you find that to be
a false false idea or do you think
that's actually our true path this is
this is what Bertrand Russell argues for
in his essay in praise of idleness this
is exactly this is 100 years old now and
he says did all we point Stu everything
so this is a hundred years ago and he
says ok everything that's wrong is the
following it everything's mass
entertainment nothing is done for itself
- you know no one's writing a book she's
writing a book because people are no
one's studying for the sake of studying
there's no art for the sake of oh yeah I
got it so he points to everything that
we're still talking about now and then
he says but the great solution will be
and there's you know a theory of
salvation once we have full technique he
says in the older English way there we
will have basically what people now call
fully automated luxury communism which
which then by the way is taken up by
Herbert makuu's a - and by Silicon
Valley
obviously Silicon Valley's but basically
just a weird amalgamation of the
Frankfurt School Marcos a and Heidegger
that's their philosophy but but what
this reveals what Russell reveals is
it's exactly this right we have not yet
met all needs and there's an interesting
essay by by Keynes who was in the same
circles
Cambridge boys as Russell where he says
around the same time we will now have to
use usury and greed for a hundred years
so that our offspring in a in 2020
around will have enough substance to
live off for the rest of eternity
it's the same idea these IP these ideas
are these notions are very old this
notion this is why I point out very
briefly and much longer in some other
essays that Plato points out the
difference between Atlantis and Athens
Atlantis sinks because they've focus
they begin to focus on lack on full
meeting all their needs and I'm not
saying that human beings don't have
needs right we do
oddly means we need to eat me to sleep
we need sex all kinds of needs met yes
but these are immediate needs and the
trouble is with our systems so called
the bf is all we focus on are these
immediate needs within which the human
being is ever only reduced to as you
know you know we're we're voters and
consumers that's who we are but we're
not allowed but but and language is
communication etc but for for someone
like Hegel it would still be to a
Nietzsche especially that the human
being is an artist first that language
is poetry first so the the it's not that
we can reach idleness isn't or leisure
that's in this true sense of Scola is
not something you can reach once
everything has been met but no it's
actually you you arrive at it and as you
arrive at this way of thinking which is
the classical way of being which means
that life is plenty be being is an
excess of itself it gifts itself and
then by by having this is where meaning
arises that's when we already know
meaning Christ is the true meaning arise
from out of this way of thinking and
then everything else flows from that
it's it's it's thinking first we
remember on the earth to speak with
Hegel not not just to do an act we're on
the earth to grasp and understand and
reason and that's what we have to do
first and then that's what then a
certain fullness comes from but if it's
if it's about trying to reach a state
where everything's mats I mean show me
show me the possibility of that because
when you start putting up conditions
off you know we need this condition in
place in this condition place then you
get the most unless any way of being
because actually what you have is a
tyranny of conditions and have to be met
yeah yeah I just I can't help shape
shake the fact that this this forgetting
seems to be pervasive on so many levels
that I'm just curious as to how are you
approaching this forgetting and trying
to bring more people into this this way
of being
in your own like practices or with with
your thinkers going yeah it's very some
level it's very simple right
it's because the question is a very
simple question so it now says if my
internet connection is unstable as if I
just let me know if it breaks down if
that even works in the I'm not sure
whether what I'm what I'm doing or
saying it you know has any bearing but
what I can say perhaps in general is
that what Heidi has says when he speaks
of the Oblivion of being he you can
translate this as saying forgetting the
old ways and and it's a quite a simple
thought
Totti na and I that which was being
being is just a different name for the
old and to make this even more like a
slogan and as you know what our but we
are always after is the new hope this is
all it the new formula of the
dishwashing tablets and and and that's
and that's that's supposed to give us
meaning the new the bats are the higher
the more superlative the bigger the
better
and but it can't be met right when you
begin to diagnose that what's always
lurking behind this is the fear not to
to be completely competing with this
right like this is why I don't like this
notion of for example the marketplace of
ideas you know ideas don't compete right
there's no competition in in thought
because truth is unitary and we
participate in it so the way that this I
think so what what what this is now this
current situation is to a certain degree
in opening right and then you can point
to certain one of the response that we
saw but it's time to build with this
essay is that what what's supposed to
happen is to have more just more
material needs met but then Andrew
pointed this out and wrote a great and I
to is we need to contemplate first how
did we get to
where we are and these are such simple
questions for example I mean even just
in terms of you know what does it mean
that we say that we live in the
Anthropocene or before that it was
called the nuclear age the nuclear epoch
where this has come from why do why is
it possible for example to set
parameters and conditions so that we can
fight these are very abstract questions
already
but for us everything in a more in a
more immediate sense the question of
being and meaning obviously is shows
itself to be very important right people
ask it seems more and more the question
of meaning and that's where you can see
an opening but then of course philosophy
as the that's the the trouble is that
there isn't a single answer but what
this is and even just the quest for
meaning is already a beginning off off
remembering and and it's a it's a it's a
remembering off off literally of you
know you yes if Plato says anamnesis of
the soul the soul begins to remember the
ideas the forms of the good the forms of
truth in the form of everything that is
and the operations of the will is
something something you can you realize
when you when you speak to people who
work a lot so I have a bit of a
philosophical practice so I talk to
people some of them tell me I have no
memory of my years of my ten years as a
lawyer because they never take the time
to slow down and think and reflect and
this is and if you look at this then on
a macro scale if you like that's where
we are we never take the time to reflect
and think back and we are and this is
why this forgetting sets in and then of
course it accelerates further etc but
right now even the Queen of England has
said this is a time to slow down so
perhaps it's and it's very fascinating
to see all of the sudden political
leaders like the Queen or today even a
Chancellor Angela Merkel in Germany
saying yeah right now we have to chair
the old the old people in that regard
and that's who are in know who are with
us and who are now lonely in their homes
because they can't be visit because they
built this country it's it's as simple
as as it can be as simple as that
it doesn't even as it doesn't have to go
into the the most you know pressing
philosophical questions but he can just
be how can I say I what is it that lets
me say that I am and that's when this
philosophical thinking perhaps them said
somebody need the stands of leisure
first yeah
Paul would you like to unmute yourself
and ask your question yeah thank you
Donna this is I I thought your reading
was incredible
all right so two questions one is are
you gonna be posting that would you
wrote I'd love to read it again and to
one of my questions is just around what
can we learn from Eastern cultures and
the sense of the spirit of non doing I
I've spent the last two years in Asia
and I found it easier to kind of
experiment with different modes of being
there in a way that I can't really
explain but it just is and I'm wondering
if you've experienced anything like that
what kind of wisdom you think we can
extract from those cultures and just any
thoughts on them yeah thank you
I will so I will publish it and good to
finally meet you all is a bit more in
person that's just on Twitter I'll post
it I know I'll link you to it so thanks
for reminding me cuz i'm i usually don't
publish this but i should i should start
doing this in terms of I will speak I've
not lived in Asia so I can't have don't
have any personal experiences but what I
see for example with someone like
[Music]
philosophy like Heidegger who is trying
to 20th century is essentially where
these worlds inevitably began to meet
and it's still occurring and we have to
so we have to be I think one has to be
strict to some degree that we are you
know there is
there is a difference and it's by
appreciating that difference though that
a genuine dialogue can set in that
that's that's I think that would be the
sort of them that's important to bear in
mind and what though what you can I
think what one can see in terms of they
have this radical fundamental difference
is that what we call the science is the
hard sciences that's that's Western that
European that's Western and it wants
what it wants is something else entirely
that when you could see with Taoism or
Buddhism which is it once control
Buddhism does not want control over
beings in their in their totality and
that's something that has begun to set
in in early modern times with in in
Europe with with Francis Bacon and
reigning de Kaap for example that's
that's basically way you can say where
this begins and where we also though
well then we could perhaps say it's fair
to say this is also where we begin to
forget but what it means to be human
because we we become a thinking thing or
as a take counts as we become pure
machines as Thomas Hobbes says or just
machines and we're also becoming more
and more divided from from nature and
from from the earth but don't forget
that for Descartes animals have
basically machines and that's very much
at the heart of of our being now is that
animals are machines plans are even you
know even less than machines for Hobbes
all we are is the state is a machine
even everything is machinery and what
one can learn I think and learning in
learning means not knowing at first and
also means a certain distance so I think
from the distance between this way of
being and the other ways of being
that's where maybe this sensation
sensation that you had off you know
other mode
of being become possible I'm sure began
to arise because it's in a certain
foreignness that one comes into one's
own it also finds though other
dimensions within oneself right because
I know your attorney a bit I can reading
your blog and everything and leaving
this path of total work behind and
finding meaning outside of this you know
what we call it the rat race and
Nietzsche calls it literally an uncanny
we work when Jaime he's a leader back in
which we are trapped and this is this is
almost 40 years ago but it is I think in
in accepting this foreignness that we
can see other ways of being yes very
much so
and it's very much I guess for now a
time to come to our own senses and at
the same time to invite this dialogue
with other ways of being because to
double down now on you know more stuff
will will not save us it will just it
and it's what do you can see with the
stock market its money thrown at it and
it's it's it's actually creating more of
a lacquer because it's creating more
debt by creating more debt we will be
and we will be we're actually gambling
away our future by creating more debt
that's literally what it is it's a bet
on the future and it creates a negative
relationship to the future already so
it's binding you towards something
that's supposed to come and it's full of
effort I think the the sometimes perhaps
the lightness of the the the far eastern
way of being but it's there's so much
true and to explore there to just in
terms of their language with the fact
that Dow means path and truth and
compass of being is yeah for me that's
that's where it's at we have to I think
what maybe want breadcrumbs to leave I
think we have to understand the
difference and similarities between
logos and the Dow
I believe it at that
interesting I think that would be
interesting to hear what you what your
perspective is and with what I'm
noticing and I guess maybe I have an eye
for Heidegger but it seems like more
people are talking about
Heidegger right now and kind of going
back to his fundamental questions about
being dwelling thinking and yeah death
death and what do you think about I mean
Heidegger coming up in conversation and
what Heidegger has to give in this
present moment I well what what his
thinking has to give this what it's
always had to give which is remembering
remembering the the fundamental question
and that's it's it's I think now it's
weird right now it's less a stroke I
said in a conversation with guys angst
or a couple weeks ago or a month ago now
that it's it's uncanny then philosophy
all of a sudden is no longer untimely
it's it's we've now entered as a sphere
where for every it'll probably be a
brief moment right there I'm where
people actually listen and are open to
an in breathing off of these questions
because but also because as I said in
the talk with the the operations of the
will to will have have stopped and in
because it I think what the fuel of this
is and I've said this in other talks the
fuel of it is boredom which then needs
to be entertained distracted from and of
course also meaninglessness if you're if
you if your life is meaningless you
consume you fill the this is what people
describe who have addictions to
consumption is that they are filling a
void a lack what Heidegger is telling us
is you know what he saw is that we don't
make ourselves is that we are not in
charge
subjectivity fools itself on the human
subject fools itself to assuming that
were fully in control and controlling
the world with Heidegger says no we're
not we're actually we're functionaries
of technics he says and his entire
philosophy and that's what my book is
about an idea is a memento mori remember
that you are mortal remember that you
are a finite being that is not in charge
but at the same time playing with forces
and powers this being has never summoned
before and this is why perhaps hiding is
now coming back up but what are your
thoughts Raven what do you think that is
well I mean the kind of uncanny thing
about this this event is that we are
confined to our homes at which brings us
into dwelling and dwelling brings us
into has I mean it opens up the
possibility of bringing us into into
being and into maybe even the
contemplation of mortality and it's this
kind of massive coordination of the
whole human population that provides us
opening for
a new way or I mean an old way of
rediscovering or remembering of this
this other way of being which is very
human and an escape I think from the
machine ik metaphor of existence which
we've just been doing and just operating
within and now we are coming back into
relationship with the the earth that
kind of biological and I find that
Heidegger was just right on in terms of
really providing and I wonder about the
German language as well because so much
of your work I find is acting as Trent
as translator for English speakers
because the German words I have so many
dimensions to them that in English
become flattened and so much of
Heidegger's thinking seems to be
dimensional oriented in landscape so so
yeah here's the difference between
English and German between the two
vernacular the German language is
spatial temporal and verbal so this
means that we very easily smash together
words yes but we also very easy to get
to this joke of haha very long German
words maybe further but also we can has
take the word
stellen which means to place or to
position now I can say here shelling and
that means to produce and then I can say
for shelling and that means to imagine
to represent but also to introduce and
all I do is add a prefix to it and it
becomes spatial temporal because the
prefix indicates a certain direction and
the direction is always spatial temporal
the English language is different the
English language finds it very difficult
to turn a verb into a noun and the
English language is ultimately
descriptive this is why it also just in
pure quantity a quantitative terms the
English language has more words it just
has a lot more words to describe things
objects and you can just
say a lot of you know beautiful
adjectives about something the German
language is very different which is why
very rarely it translates and then also
about the English language lacks
entirely is self-reflective verbs
suburbs that necessarily reflect or come
back to themselves which is why so much
is often lost and then I buy you know a
series of accidents and contingencies
I've ended up speaking both languages
well enough to perhaps be this
transmitter in between but you know in
terms of hiding hiding ask this word of
air I guess and people have translated
this as event but now I can this means
he says that which comes into its own
acid withdraws so right now we're in a
moment of utter withdrawal but at the
same time and this also comes back to a
question from sort of question from Paul
and this withdrawal we're coming back
into our own and then here we are to
complement my my answer from before in
the dialogue with Buddhism for example
because Buddhism is a thinking of
withdrawing is a thinking of not
non-availability and that's that's where
we need to get to in the West is to
think understand and appreciate
concealment unavailability withdrawal
because we want this total availability
and access and you know control over it
and that's that's that's disappeared all
right and now we're in this abeyance but
we don't get know what's what's going to
we can't even make me usually you make
plans right now I'm going to be at a
wedding in two months and I'm gonna be
I'm gonna be traveling to Italy in two
years you don't even know where I'm
gonna what I'm gonna be able to fly back
to Germany so yeah old all the planning
is out the window it's it's literally
day-to-day now and yeah yeah sense of
future has like fundamentally changed
yes yes Andrew would you like to meet
yourself and ask a question
hi Joanna's great presentation I've been
following some of your content on
YouTube which is which is great as well
so I just wanted to ask do you think
this idea of being conflicts with our
evolutionary drive for status in our
driver to move up the social hierarchy
because I think at our core you know
humans are status seeking animals and I
see this potential conflict between our
sort of evolutionary drives and this
idea to you know adopt a an idea of
being or being in the present moment or
or what not okay what do you mean by
being I guess perhaps Heidegger's notion
of being yeah we just want I'll
personally I haven't read Heidegger but
I guess sort of what you were trying to
get at it what we were getting at in
that lecture like let's say I think he
uses the word dasya design
yeah yeah design is the being of the
human being and that's a regular German
word it's the openness to the ver of
being but you see when you ask the
question what you're what the question
does is it posits that there's the
evolutionary drive for status that's not
questioned but that's so what do you
have what one has to do in a
philosophical question is first to
question the question why is it is it
true fundamentally true that all we do
is social hierarchy or status is is this
all the human beings do is this true for
all human beings across all
civilizations is this true for what we
what we have original societies is that
the case is is that the chorus is only
the case for perhaps competitive
capitalist societies in which that's
that's that kind of status seeking is
rewarded and is this perhaps not the
case for even for a country up until
this day like Italy where or or Spain or
Japan but people don't thinks in terms
don't think in terms of jobs but in
terms of roles that they take in their
community right I have a certain role to
fulfill and and then the question of
being has to do with the question of
meaning that's what it ultimately is and
I don't so you can you could have even
within you know this this framework the
drive for status which human beings have
to some degree but not only I don't
think that's the only thing that's
driving history even that can be just
can reveal something about meaning and
what it means to be human but that's not
the only dimension we're in right we're
because there are more moments I would
think that might not be recorded in
history where human beings do something
not at all to find status or social
hierarchy or caring for the elderly is
not highly status rewarding and still
people do it and and luckily because if
not everything would break down and
actually societies that don't do this
they break down all right this is North
America in a nutshell is it's just you
know give me my my money in my career
and I will not care for the elderly
it's I don't think that that's a very
sustainable Society anyways thank you
yeah I'm finally yo.hannes I just wanted
to ask you about how you're addressing
the failure of our act or the capture of
our academic institutions or the places
of where we're thinking ought to dwell
[Laughter]
Manchester is a case is you know oh
we're losing trying to fifty million
pounds this year so we're going to fire
people that there was their response
just today so yeah please go on sorry oh
and I just saw in the chat that Andre
has a question so we're gonna I'm gonna
let Andre ask that question here and
probably the final one so Andre please
know you wanted to ask okay yeah can you
hear me okay yes so this is probably a
bit of a semantic question idleness
I would probably define as a negation of
something so to be idle is to not do
something yeah and would there be a
delineation between having passive
idleness and active idleness because
would not one be just the lack of your
being to in act on something passive
idleness so it's your being is not
acting on anything it's just being
itself whereas in active violence you're
using part of your define so to speak or
one part of your being to actively
not do something mm-hmm oh okay I'll try
and answer this I think first of all I
would think that's a fair description of
it and of course idleness has these
negative connotations in the English
vernacular for the most part now but so
I'm not so this is why I've used the
word I've said scholar very often or the
true spirit of leisure which is only
just an approximation also for the
Greeks mean bicycle but I think idleness
to make this a bit clearer and this
comes back to what Paul said tunes what
do you say also is that it's you know
the idol stands first to be idle means
to move away from the immediate demands
from for example the world to will right
and by moving away from these immediate
demands by denying them their power in
this idle stance we then perhaps come
into the the meditative mode if you like
of which in which then meaning arises
that is completely divided from the
question of usefulness and utility yeah
yeah yeah just addendum to your question
okay
yeah you should read you will find a PDF
off peepers book on line letter as the
basis of culture chose it yeah it's a
it's a definitely recommend it's a short
and much more accessible than you'd
expect
yeah it's a very good essay never got
raven always your question on was this
poll set but nothing i'm not gonna take
you to I mean there's just so much in
this whole range of ideas that you're
getting into right now and he's like
fundamental questions
there's so many just mirages of thought
to to shatter and to you know try and
subvert so many levels of it and yeah so
in the case of institutions I just see
that you're you're attempting to
experiment with different models I mean
your your thinkers guild I think is a
great example of trying to create
something outside of academic
institutions where people can actually
engage in the process of dialogue and
thinking about the you know classical
engagement with with ideas and with
being without being subject to
abstraction and and like categorization
and ranking based on their performance
within that within that realm so if if
you just have a few things you like to
say about that right here in the last
few minutes we you mentioned something I
would have forgotten which is rankings
rankings is exactly this kind of making
everything useful a wonderful essay and
people can email me and I'll send it to
them I'm not finding it now of course is
written by eva de janeiro which is
entitled the fiction of peer review so
even peer review but just you know it's
no longer a peer who is a peer appear is
you know you and pizza you've very
likely peers in the store you are
co-hosting the stoah as peers and you
are inviting me on and to give a talk
and others too and they become your
peers in the process which means that
there is the possibility to in a
trusting relationship to disagree that's
important that's what academia needs
that that's what an academia multum
utley means philosophy and that that's
what thinking needs right it can't just
be this the self-serving circles which
of course we have because we need
citation rings in order to be ranked
highly and in its functions
gatekeeping so we can talk about that
but then of course you also have this
this very sick slogan of publish or
perish
so if you don't publish you perish
that's the opposite of the the idle
observer that you know from the
philosophical life is the highest form
of theoria as aristotle says which means
to observe the world if the philosopher
has to produce papers is no longer a
philosopher the philosopher that
produces papers is isn't some sort of
Jim it's a journalist or something and
the peer that it so it's everything's
perverted but it uses these let these
words that are very meaningful and
profound and and wonderful but it
perverts them the the peers and also
everything is full of pressure
everything is a burden right teaching is
described by academics as a burden I'll
have to teach again and it's when it's
week nine here in the UK many was out
week nine because it's just one more
week of teaching and then finally my
teaching load when it's teaching load
it's all these words it's so ridiculous
the teaching is not a load right if you
are a teacher then you read and then you
write and then you teach and after
teaching so I got some you know not
feedback I refuse now to use cybernetic
language I've gotten now responses and
more questions so I will go back
afterwards and rewrite the essay and
then I will publish it to get again
responses to it and that's that's the
that's the wholeness of of teaching and
I've never found it possible
unfortunately within academic so also
because they don't like accent excited
eccentric types are now forbidden right
so that's and that makes it difficult
for me and when I try to publish my book
on on Heidegger with finger which I
think they will now publish they made it
the the reviewers who I've never met one
of them was okay and the other one was
just violent the violence was you did he
did not mention this author and not this
author not this book and not this book
that was the entire review of course I
haven't mentioned everyone and
everything that you think is you know
where this is
peer review and the violence comes in
because it is anonymous in this
anonymity is that that's where that's
actually where the entire idea of the
Academy breaks down the Academy of the
original Academy the Academy have played
to access it for hundreds of years and
they all disagreed with him so it's not
it's not about you know here's the dogma
you read it and and take you take my
word for it no it isn't this profound
peer based disagreement which only can
happen when you actually trust someone
but not an easy you know violent
operations of trying to gauge keep
certain ways of thinking or so do you
brought up the you know the the question
of language between Heidegger and the
German vernacular in the English there
are certain ways of thinking about
Heidegger that are not thereafter that
are for bohtan in English academic
circles because they would be closer to
the Chairman and you can't think like
this but actually if you begin to think
off the history of being not as a
history but as the tidings of be and
right now we live through an ebbing away
of being it begins to make more sense
and you know you were a student on the
Heidegger de leurs course and McCoy that
artist from New York recently sent me a
tweet saying understanding Gish tell as
the concentration of positioning makes
such a big difference because you begin
to see very differently in when you
think of it as in framing is like
something coming from the outside and
but kind of like overpowering but now
it's actually much worse right it's much
more subtle it's in it's in it's in how
things appear and are and with the guilt
it's basically just you know the guild
guilds were what build the first
universities so I don't know where this
is going to lead of course but as a
guilt it just brings together people so
for example we're doing a book
publication next week Shawn Burke's an
artist from Pasadena he's written a book
winter and summer you know remembering
who we are is basically the subtitle and
aesthetics of memory I think is a
subtitle that'll be out next week so
we'll do book publications and course
listen we'll see her release is just
bringing a couple of eccentric types
together and then those eccentric types
they can maybe build the next university
because what we're seeing now is if they
fire that many people they're using pure
market terms it's pure market logic
that's how you destroy a brand and so
for the coming decades I'm I think that
you know private or or cooperative
education then doesn't thrive because
people are open to it this is why the
the store is so fascinating because
people are coming to to these talks that
maybe wouldn't have come half a year ago
yeah absolutely all right I'm going to
tell us a little bit about the day and
what other events will be happening at
the stove here so and thank you Johannes
for joining us I feel like what you're
bringing voice to in this like space is
very very important and there's a lot to
talk about
so I really appreciate that and let me
tell you about upcoming events here so
we have human systems live action
redesign with a marine cell cat 12 I'm
just gonna jump in that let's cancel
that one okay and then the existential
dance party is canceled as well okay so
we have Sam oh right
yes Sam oh that's the only one okay so
reform of government institution I think
that bad dovetails very well with the
conversation we're having about the
Academy Academy right now so that's
gonna be later at 4:00 p.m. Eastern Time
so if you would like to join us for that
you can RSVP at the stowage EA and there
are also many more events coming on the
horizon so thank you all for being here
and I just wanted to propose an idea so
I'm kind of Peter and I are working on
this idea of like bringing people in to
have a conversation and then opening it
up more to like a seminar like dialog
and I was just gonna Steve Yohannes if
you have like 15 minutes or something
where you just wanted to kind of open up
to a conversation after this totally up
to you um I thought I would I would make
the invitation yeah okay great let's do
it